Guide to the Jones Graduate School of Management Images Collection, 1977-2003 UA 402
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jones Graduate School of Management image collection
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 402
2.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes
The collection consists of images in a variety of formats of people, buildings, and events and programs associated with the Jones Graduate School of Business since its early years in the laste seventies until the first decade of the 2000s.
Biographical / Historical
Although the goal of establishing a business school at Rice had been set in the sixties during the admihnistration of University President Kenneth Pitzer, the challenge of raising sufficient funds was not fully met until large gifts like a pledge of $5 million by Houston Endowment, Inc. had been secured in the mid-70's. The intent of this gift was to honor the memory of Jesse H. Jones, one of Houston's most important business and civic leaders and the founder of the Endowment. Thus, the Rice Board named the new school the Jesse H. Jones Graduate School of Administration. In April 1876 Robert R. Sterling, already at Rice as the first Jesse H. Jones Professor of Management and chairman of the accounting department, was named the first dean. In this early period there were two main goals: to develop a coherent curriculum and to build on the Houston Endowment $5 million gift to raise the endowment to levels adequate to support the school's ongoing expenses.
Classes began with 55 students in 1977. Two degrees were offered, the Master of Business and Public Management and the Master of Accounting. In July 1980 Dean Sterling left the Jones, School, having built an excellent faculty, attracted good students, and seen the school begin to achieve a solid reputation in the Houston area.
The primary goal of a second phase, which was to last through the next 15 years and the next two deans, was to realize the ambition for national prominence. Dean Sterling was succeeded by Doug Tuggle, who had been the school's associate dean since 1978 and interim dean in the 1980-81 academic year. He served until 1987, when Rice chose former Postmaster General Benjamin F. Bailar to lead the school. In the intervening period the school moved away from its intense focus on public policy, and in the fall of 1985 the university faculty approved a change in the degree offered by the Jones School from Master of Business Management and Public Management to Master of Business Administration. Additionally, the school opened its own placement office (instead of depending on the university's placement personnel). After a major fundraising effort, the goal of $10 million for a new building and an endowment for its maintenance was reached. Herring Hall, the Jones' School new home, was completed in 1984.
Dean Bailar's administration, lasting until his retirment in 1997, was a period of gradual improvements in program offerings including cooperation with Rice's George R. Brown School of Engineering to offer a joint MBA/Master of Engineering degree. However, the challenges were still not enough to bring the Jones School to the level of being regarding nationally as an elite program.
The arrival of Rice's sixth president, Malcolm Gillis, in 1993, along with Dean Bailar's 1995 paper "Recognition for Excellence," prompted a thorough review of the school. The conclusion of the review was that the Jones School should either "embark on a course of becoming recognized for world-class distinctiveness and quality in management education, or it should decide to close its doors." Determination to follow the first of these alternatives led to commitment by President Gillis and a steering committee to make changes that would take advantage of the school's unique situation in relation to the Houston business community.
The retirement of Dean Bailar was followed by selection of Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr., a 1953 Rice graduate who as dean of the University of Michigan Business School for nearly 12 years had led that institution to become one of the top business schools in the country. Dean Whitaker announced the goal of being ranked as a top-ten business school within 10 years. He began by leading the school to obtain International Association for Management Education accreditation in 1998. The planning included an increase in the number of studnets and faculty, which, along with changes in technology, made it necessary to anticipate replacing Herring Hall with a new building designed with state of the art facilities for a premier program. Ground was broken on the new building on May 23, 2000, and in August 2002, the school occupied was has become known as McNair Hall.
With these developments, the Jones Graduate School of Business, as it has been known since 2017, has come as close as at any time in its history to being the nationally ranked enterprise envisioned by its leaders since its inception.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of images in a variety of formats of people, buildings, and events and programs associated with the Jones Graduate School of Business since its early years in the laste seventies until the first decade of the 2000s.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by the Jones Graduate School of Business in 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
photographs
Places
Rice University
Subjects (Corporations)
Jesse H. Jones Graduate School of Administration
- Series I. Image collection
  - Faculty: Allen (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Faculty: Jeffrey D. Anderlik (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty: Keith Anderson (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty: Arbogast (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty: Atherton (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Faculty: Attwell (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Faculty: Austgen (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dean's Seminar: Nathan Avery (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Faculty: Bagozzi (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Faculty: Benjamin Bailar (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dean's Seminar: Benjamin Bailar (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dean's Lecture: Keith Bailey (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean's Lecture Series: Keith Bailey, Williams CEO 10/3/2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James A. Baker III (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Faculty: J. Baker (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - L. Baker (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dean's Seminar: Walter Baker, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty: Banks (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty: Barrett (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dean's Seminar: Thomas Barrow (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carin Barth, GWIB speaker, 9/13/2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Faculty: Batsell (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Faculty: Phillip Bell (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dean's Seminar: Terry Bell (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dean's Seminar: Berman (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dean's Seminar: Bernard (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dean's Lecture: Gordon Bethune (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jeff Bezos, guest speaker, Amazon, 9/5/2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dean's Lecture: Jeff Bezos (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dean's Lecture: Bintliff (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dean's Seminar: James Bitonti (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dean's Seminar: Blanton (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dean's Lecture: Michael Bloomberg (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dean's Seminar: Blumenthal (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Faculty: Boon (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dean's Lecture: Garrett Boone (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Dean's Seminar: Bossarge (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dean's Lecture: Greg Brenneman (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Faculty: Brenner (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dean's Seminar: Lee Brown (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dean's Seminar: R.S. Brown (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dean's Seminar: Sarah Brown (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Dean's Seminar: Gordon Cain (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dean's Seminar: Michael Capellas (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dean's Seminar: Cashen (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Ken Chenault (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Dean's Seminar: Cisneros (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Faculty: Clayton (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Dean's Seminar: Abby Cohn (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Dean's Seminar: Creuzot (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Faculty: Currall (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Faculty: Currall, Cheyanne (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Dean's Seminar: Doug Daft (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Faculty: Daley (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Dean's Seminar: Deily (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Dean's Seminar: DeJoria (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Jill Deuster (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Dean's Lecture: Dewy (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Faculty: Dharan (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Dean's Seminar: Diener (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - J. Hank Diesel (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Edward Djerejian (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Dean's Seminar: Douglas (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Charles Duncan (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Faculty: Durovich (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Ralph Eads, El Paso, 4/11/2001 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Faculty: Epstein (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Dean's Seminar: Farfel (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Faculty: Finger (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Fiorina (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Faculty: Fleming (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Faculty: Garson (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Faculty: George (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Lisa Gibbons (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Faculty: Gill (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Dean's Lecture Series: Allan Gilmore, 1/22/2003 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Dean's Seminar: Gilmour (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Faculty: Grullon (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hall (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Halliburton (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Faculty: Hankamer (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Faculty: Hannan (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Dean's Lecture: Bill Hannigan, CEO Sabre, 9/4/2002 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hay (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Faculty: Hebl (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Dean's Seminar: Richard Heckert (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Faculty: Heeley (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Faculty: Hemeyer (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hengst (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hines (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Dean's Seminar: Honig (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Dean's Seminar: Howe (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Faculty: Hua (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hunt (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hutchison (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Faculty: Ikenberry (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - David Ikenberry (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Dean's Seminar: Ikle (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Dean's Seminar: Gerald Irons (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Faculty: Jackson (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Faculty: Neelah Jain (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Faculty: Jett (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Dean's Seminar: Jordan (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Dean's Seminar: Kanas (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Faculty: Kantas (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Dean's Seminar: Kelley (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Dean's Seminar: Ketelsen (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Dean's Seminar: Kieschnik (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Dean's Seminar: Kinnear (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Faculty: Klein (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Faculty: Krishnan (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Faculty: Kumar (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Dean's Seminar: Lassiter (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Dean's Seminar: Laurenzo (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Faculty: Lawrence (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Dean's Seminar: Kenneth Lay (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Dean's Seminar: Mickey Leland (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Dean's Seminar: Liedtke (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Faculty: Love (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Dean's Seminar: Lucas (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Dean's Seminar: J. Mackey (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Faculty: Mandel (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Dean's Seminar: Rebecca Mark (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Dean's Lecture Series: Drayton McLane, Jr., 9/6/2000 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Faculty: McAshan (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Faculty: McCabe (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Faculty: McDonald (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Dean's Seminar: McDonald (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Dean's Seminar: Mednick (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Dean's Seminar: Lasker Meyer (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Faculty: Miller (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Dean's Seminar: Miller (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Guest speaker: Steve Miller, 1/30/2003 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Dean's Seminar: Judith Munson (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Faculty: Murphree (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Faculty: Mutisik (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Faculty: Napier (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Dean's Seminar: O'Connor (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Dean's Seminar: Orton (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Faculty: Ostdick (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Dean's Seminar: Ostrum-George (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Faculty: O'Sullivan (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Dean's Seminar: Otto (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Faculty: Parke (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dean's Seminar: Cesar Pelli (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dean's Seminar: Perry (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty: Peters (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dean's Seminar: T. Boone Pickens (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dean's Seminar: Pieper (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty: Quinones (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dean's Seminar: Raffens Perger (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - James Rahe (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Faculty: Ramnath (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty: Rasmussen (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dean's Seminar: Robinson (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Faculty: Ross (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Faculty: Russo (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dean's Seminar: Sakowitz (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dean's Seminar: Schadewald (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Faculty: Schnietz (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Faculty: Schuler (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dean's Seminar: Lee Seidler (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Faculty: Shook (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Faculty: Silverman (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dean's Seminar: Smith (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Dean's Seminar: Solomons (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Faculty: Sood (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Dean's Seminar: Sprouse (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Dean Sterling (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dean's Seminar: Stone (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Dean's Seminar: Tatron (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Faculty: Taylor (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Faculty: Thrall (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Dean's Seminar: Tucker (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Dean's Lecture: Jim Turley, 12/11/2000 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Faculty: Uecker (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Dean's Seminar: Hal Varion (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Faculty: Viebig (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Faculty: Wagner (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Faculty: Wallach (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Dean's Seminar: Walsh (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Faculty: Wang (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Faculty: Westbrook (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Faculty: Westheimer (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Dean's Seminar: Wheeler (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Gil Whitaker (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Gil Whitaker and others (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dean's Seminar: Whitmire (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Faculty: Williams (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Faculty: Windsor (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Dean's Seminar: Wolf (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Dean's Seminar: Wright (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Faculty: Zeff (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Dean's Lecture: Sam Zell, 2/12/2003 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Faculty (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Various faculty in groups (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Staff (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Jones School staff with Dean Whitaker (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Students in class (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Dean's Seminars: Multiples (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Herring Hall (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Herring Hall architectural details (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Herring Hall courtyard (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Students and Herring Hall (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - McNair Hall during construction (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Jones Graduate School building (McNair Hall) interior and exterior (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - McNair Hall interior and exterior (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Jones Graduate School (McNair Hall) and Dean Whitaker bust (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Rice campus (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - 1983-1990 OED programs (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1983-1990 The Management Program and Business (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dean Sterling; open house Herring Hall BIC, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 10th anniversary (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reception for Dean Whitaker (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Investiture, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Enron event (Box 3, Envelope 7-8)
  - Gil Whitaker's birthday party, 2001-10 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dedication, 2002-09-18 (Box 3, Envelope 10)
  - McNair Hall dedication (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Neuhaus lectures (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Jones School brochure (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Unknown events (Box 3, Folder 14)